Something crazy just happened
to GoPro, and I think a lot
of people missed a very important detail.
Markiplier posted a sponsored GoPro video,
and days later, everyone found out
he was GoPro's biggest shareholder.
The stock more than doubled in two days.
Then, out of nowhere, GoPro agreed to merge,
with a company almost no one had heard of.
All within about five days.
People were confused, and a bit suspicious.
Some began to ask: “Did Markiplier pump and dump?”
But, I think, Mark might be the least
strange part of this whole thing.
There’s something everyone seemed to miss.
GoPro's margins had fallen
from 32% to 4% in a year.
That company they merged with was
incorporated the day before the deal.
And GoPro is staying on the stock market?
What the heck is going on at GoPro?
So, to understand all these wild events,
let’s go back to that first video.
On August 27th, Markiplier
uploaded a sponsored GoPro video.
A very normal, inconspicuous
video. But immediately after,
a weird series of events took place.
On August 31st, Bloomberg reported that
Mark had accumulated an 8.5% stake in GoPro.
Markiplier told Bloomberg, “It blows my mind
what it can do in such a small package,”
“They have a big future with this camera
coming out opening up a new segment for them.”
He also said, “I saw the stock and where it was,
I was like that seems undervalued. It’s
just something I’ve been cooking in the
background; I want the company to succeed.”
Within a day, the media all began sharing it.
“8.5% stake”, “biggest
shareholder”, “Undervalued”.
This sent the stock into a frenzy.
The stock closed up 46% on August
31st, then another 80% on September 1st.
Then, on September 1st, GoPro announced it would
be merging, with a company called Starman Optical.
They said “shareholders will receive an aggregate
cash payment of $285 million, or $1.14 per share”
At this price, Markiplier will get $15 million.
Business Insider estimated his
profit at about $5 million.
At this point, a bunch of people began
to notice this pattern of events.
So… did Markiplier pump & dump everybody?
Mark had been accumulating stock for months.
So no. Not by a long shot, did he pump and dump.
It was July 13th that he had reached the amount
that triggered a disclosure obligation.
Then, after a lot of processing time,
his ownership was made public
on August 20th (show last page).
He also told Business Insider, "I'm not
going to lie, I'm disappointed, [about the
merger]" "I would vote against the deal."
But, he couldn’t do anything about it.
He had acquired Class A shares, meaning even
though he was the largest shareholder, he only
had a small amount of voting power, compared
to Class B shares, which get 10 votes each.
And when you take a step back… Markiplier
investing in GoPro, makes a lot of sense.
He’s done some extremely ambitious projects
over the years, most of all: Iron Lung.
A professional, self-funded, self-acted,
written, and directed feature-length film,
which grossed over $50 million at the box
office… with around a $5 million budget.
Some of the special effects were rendered using
a whole bunch of Mac Studios, in his bathroom.
This is the story of this funny
photo of him showing Tim Cook
So, a filmmaker investing in a camera
company, which is also producing more
filmmaking equipment, makes a lot of sense.
So, did Mark do anything illegal? No.
He didn’t pump the stock, and
had no involvement in the merger,
and a stock will always jump when word
gets out a big name invests in it.
But… even though the GoPro video
was clearly disclosed as sponsored,
he probably should have clearly disclosed that he
was also a GoPro shareholder in the sponsor video.
The FTC states that “if you endorse
a product through social media,
your endorsement message should make
it obvious when you have a relationship
(“material connection”) with the brand.”
He has this “material connection” to GoPro,
and directly benefits from the profitability
and perception of the GoPro brand, and thus,
has a higher incentive to showcase that.
Though, this doesn’t prove illegality,
and he did add it shortly after.
So maybe a slight slip-up, but I
see no malicious intent here, nothing illegal.
I genuinely think Mark liked GoPro products,
invested, and the news broke,
right as the merger happened.
But, this is actually just the tip of the iceberg.
Some pretty insane things have been going on,
independent of Mark.
For one, GoPro, has been barely surviving.
In Q1 of 2026, they lost $81
million, on revenue of $99 million!
But the reason is what’s weird. GoPro is
struggling for a very particular reason,
mostly out of their control.
And that’s not all.
The other “merging” company, was
incorporated on August 31st, 2026…
One day before the merger.
Then merged with GoPro… which is
still traded as a public company?
So, what really happened?
Well… this wasn’t really a merger,
at all. It’s closer to a “takeover…”
Let’s get a little bit of context.
GoPro’s sudden jump after the
investment, sure sounds like a lot.
GoPro stock closed 46% higher on Aug 31
and the next day, jumped another 80%.
That sounds huge…
…until you see the bigger picture
The first jump was to 88 cents, and
that 80% jump… was only to $1.58.
So… 80% of basically nothing.
GoPro, had collapsed, long
before Markiplier invested.
But, it was in a way worse
spot than people realise.
GoPro was once the unicorn of unicorns.
It exploded with a great product,
an untapped market, and great branding.
But… they gradually fumbled their spot at the top,
fell behind, and soon competitors got ahead.
But what matters for us today, is how bad things
had gotten, in 2026, and this time,
it’s hard to say it’s GoPro’s fault.
In GoPro’s Q2 financial statements,
they said this fairly candidly.
“The company’s performance continued to be
adversely impacted by an increasingly global
competitive landscape, consumer-related
macroeconomic issues resulting in a
softer global consumer market, rising
memory costs and supply constraints. ”
Their net loss for the first quarter, was $81
million, on revenue of $99 million. Not good.
In the same quarter last year,
they also had a $47 million loss.
So, why was GoPro struggling?
There’s a multitude of reasons:
a softer market, a more saturated market.
But there’s one specific, recent problem.
One of the biggest, is “rising memory costs”.
Their gross margin, aka revenue minus cost of
making the product, was just 4.3%.
But the weird part, is that margin
was as high as 32.1% a year earlier.
“the Company’s forecast has been significantly
impacted by [quote continues…] continued increases
and volatility in memory costs, including an
initial unexpected price increases ranging from
80% to 115% in the last week of March 2026."
The CFO also said:
[Brian Tratt. Chief Financial Officer,
GoPro]: "Memory pricing increased from a range
of 80% to 115% in the last week of the quarter."
In just the last week. Crazy.
GoPro, as you may have guessed,
doesn’t build its own memory. Very
likely DRAM for its camera processors.
It commits to buying a set quantity in advance,
at a set price, on terms it can't cancel.
In April 2026, GoPro's memory suppliers
told it they were reducing production
of the memory used in its products.
But, memory costs rise 80 to 115% in
a week. GoPro is stuck. It already promised to buy
a certain amount, for a certain number of cameras.
And now it can't afford to make that many.
This is why in Q1, they had to write off
a loss of $24.5 million on components
they had ordered and couldn't cancel.
That’s why their gross margin had
fallen almost 90% in one year.
So GoPro built fewer cameras, because there
wasn't enough memory left to build them with.
Memory suppliers were producing
less of the memory GoPro needed.
And can you guess why?
They were putting most of their
capacity towards memory for data centres.
Still, there was a bit of hope.
Q2 subscription and services revenue was up 11% to
about $29.0 million, and made up 28% of revenue,
against 17% a year earlier.
That’s great.
But hardware revenue was falling a
lot. From $126 million in Q2 2025,
to just $76 million in Q2 2026.
So… why acquire this struggling camera company?
Starman Optical, the company that
merged with GoPro… what did they want?
Well, remember, this company
was incorporated a day before.
This wasn’t really a merger, at all.
And Starman wasn’t here for the cameras.
But something else.
If you’ve watched this far,
consider subscribing! It helps the channel
and means you won’t miss future videos.
Everyone is talking about a GoPro “merger”,
and legally, it is a “merger”… But it wasn’t.
It was a takeover.
Starman Optical,
incorporated August 31st, in Delaware, is
actually a subsidiary of Action Acquisitions LLC.
So, a new acquisition shell was formed to
merge with GoPro, which itself disappears
as a separate legal company.
But, in reality, this was
Action Acquisitions, acquiring GoPro.
This is a standard legal mechanism called
a reverse subsidiary merger. The buyer
creates a subsidiary, merges it into the
target, and the target survives.
But GoPro would keep the name.
They’d also… stay a public company?
Not only that, there was a $285 million
cash payment to GoPro shareholders, at $1.14
per share, hence the profit Markiplier got.
And, there was about $92 million of
GoPro debt to be repaid at closing.
So why?
Why do all this?
Well, if we look at GoPro’s announcement,
Starman Optical is a “Starman Holding company”,
and somewhere inside that structure, is “Starman
New Photonics.” This entity is “focused on the
development and domestic manufacturing of optical
transceivers and related photonics technologies”
All of this is under Action Acquisitions,
although we don’t quite know the exact structure.
Point is, Starman New
Photonics, optical transceivers.
Essential pieces of hardware,
to convert electrical signals,
into light pulses for fibre-optic cables.
It’s essential in sending huge
amounts of data, very, very fast.
Does this sound familiar? It should,
because there’s something everyone’s
building to process lots and lots of data…
Let’s look at GoPro’s press release again.
“Transaction Expected to Add U.S. Onshore
Optical Transceiver Business, Positioning
GoPro to Expand into AI Data Center markets”
“Advanced optics and imaging are essential to AI”.
GoPro was acquired, not because of its cameras,
but its optics and imaging technology.
It has 2,500 U.S. patents, many of them
around this technology.
And that’s not all.
Remember how GoPro is still a public company?
GoPro’s existing shareholders would hold
about 10% of the company post-merger.
Action Acquisitions/Starman’s owners would
hold the other roughly 90%.
But why stay public?
Listing a business on the Nasdaq takes
a lot of time, and costs a lot of money,
including lots of bank fees, regulatory
filings, marketing, more investor scrutiny…
By merging into GoPro, Starman can gain
control of an already listed company instead.
But doing this means they don’t get
to raise money through an IPO? So why?
Well, it gives owners publicly tradable shares
to sell, and a “stock currency” to compensate
employees, raise capital, or buy other companies.
And this is especially important, with them being
a photonics/AI-infrastructure company.
A reverse-merger route is often faster
and cheaper than an IPO, even if it
doesn’t itself raise new money on day one.
And that’s a part no one seemed to notice.
This wasn’t just Starman merging with GoPro. It
was Starman skipping an IPO, and turning GoPro’s
trading stock… partly into the Starman stock.
Markiplier voted against the
merger, and I understand why.
GoPro is, but also isn’t really,
a camera company now. Though,
they definitely won’t be stopping
that side of the business.
But, I don’t think GoPro would
have survived without this merger.
GoPro’s action-camera category is mature
and fiercely competitive, particularly
against companies such as DJI and Insta360.
AI optics are a much bigger strategic bet.
The larger question though, is how did GoPro fall
so far behind? Well, that story is even stranger.
A huge IPO, then huge talk of moving beyond
a camera company, to a “media company”…
then a strange, total collapse.
To learn the rest of the story,
watch this video next.
Or, if you’d like a video
where a single YouTube review seemed to kill
an entire EV brand, you can watch this video.